<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<title><![CDATA[arvydasg.github.io]]></title>
<description><![CDATA[arvydasg.github.io]]></description>
<link>https://arvydasg.github.io/</link>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 11:22:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[naujas postas]]></title>
  <description><![CDATA[
<p>
Hello this is a new blogpost. Just checking it out you know.
</p>
<div class="taglist"><a href="https://arvydasg.github.io/tags.html">Tags</a>: <a href="https://arvydasg.github.io/tag-emacs.html">emacs</a> <a href="https://arvydasg.github.io/tag-nixos.html">nixos</a> </div>]]></description>
  <category><![CDATA[emacs]]></category>
  <category><![CDATA[nixos]]></category>
  <link>https://arvydasg.github.io/2023-12-12-naujas-postas.html</link>
  <guid>https://arvydasg.github.io/2023-12-12-naujas-postas.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 11:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[Black Box Method]]></title>
  <description><![CDATA[

<figure id="orgbc80025">
<img src="./static/images/squirrel.png" alt="squirrel.png" width="1200px">

</figure>

<p>
Main inspiration - <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RDzsrmMl48I&amp;t=604s">this guy</a>.
</p>

<p>
A guy that explained this concept to me is competing in coding
competitions. It's the first time I hear about those, but I imagine
you have to know a lot of different methods for solving problems,
because when the contest comes, you don’t know what problem you are
going to get.
</p>

<p>
Recently, when I started to think about effective ways of learning a
new subject, I came up to people saying to learn things broadly, to
just scratch the surface of the new subjects instead of what I used to
always do - learn as much as I can (like a squirrel with cheeks full
of nuts) about a topic. According to them, after having general
knowledge of the field/s you can take up a project and deepen the
knowledge along the way.
</p>

<p>
So let's say there is a field that I want to get into. Conveniently I
have such a field - Data science. Data science includes many topics:
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li>Mathematics</li>
<li>Statistics</li>
<li>Programming languages (Python, R)</li>
<li>Data cleanign and visualization - (Pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib, Seaborn)</li>
<li>Exploring the data (SQL)?</li>
<li>Machine learnign algorithms</li>
<li>Deep learning (all about neural networks)</li>
<li>SQL &amp; MongoDb (working with databases)</li>
<li>BI tools (creating interactive visualizations)</li>
</ul>

<p>
and so on…
</p>

<p>
So, If I want to get into the field AND I am learning by myself from
scratch, creating my own small project and working on it. Would it be
smart for me to start with and dive very very deep in mathematics?
Know the ins and outs of it needed for data science?
</p>

<p>
As I came to see it, it is worth investing some time to explore ALL
those major fields BEFORE you actually proceed to learn one specific
topic in depth.
</p>

<p>
Why is that?
</p>

<p>
Well, If for example I get a piece of data from somewhere (I am still
working on that.. Not sure how, what kind and from where to get it)
and I am only focusing on mathematics, I won’t know what else exactly
is there I can do with that piece of data. Can I create a
visualization, can I make a dashboard or reports, can I get some
insights from it? I lack a lot of general knowledge, all I know is
math.
</p>


<figure id="orgba3c9e0">
<img src="./static/images/black-box1.png" alt="black-box1.png" width="1200px">

</figure>

<p>
I learn concept-1 (mathematics), but the rest of the topics are
unknown to me.
</p>

<p>
Would it be smart if I take concept-2 and concept-3 from the unknown
row and only then proceed with learning one topic in depth. In that
case, I have knowledge of all of the topics, broad knowledge (I am
going to learn it in depth anyway, so it's only good that I started to
learn it already) so if sa project or a difficulty appears, I know
about the possible tools I have in my reach that I can use to solve
the problem. Yes, I don’t have an in depth knowledge of concept-2 and
concept-3, but it is better than not having ANY knowledge.
</p>

<p>
So, okay.
</p>

<p>
This is what I am going to do. I will spend the next few days getting
an understanding of those fields I mentioned above, so when I am
solving a particular problem related with data, I will have an idea
what else is there that is possible to achieve with the data that I
have.
</p>

<p>
It's an easy gap to cross versus understanding the whole thing. Black
box all the concepts before starting to fully learn them. It is not a
substitute for learning them, just for the start.
</p>

<p>
It is an intermediate step, except it has no drawbacks, you are going
to learn this stuff anyway. So it is only going to benefit you.
</p>

<p>
<b>Advantages</b>
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li>Works quickly - information required to USE something is much less
than the information required to fully understand something.</li>

<li>Keeps the learning focused - you know what everything is “doing”,
you know what purpose of it is. All you are doing when you are
transitioning from having something black boxed to learning it
norma+lly - you are just figuring out how it works. You already know
what it does, you already know everything required to use it, you
are just understanding the internal mechanisms of it.</li>

<li>Keeps the learning focused - you know what everything is “doing”,
you know what purpose of it is. All you are doing when you are
transitioning from having something black boxed to learning it
norma+lly - you are just figuring out how it works. You already know
what it does, you already know everything required to use it, you
are just understanding the internal mechanisms of it</li>

<li>Makes learning less scary - when you understand the underlying
purpose of something it makes it a lot less scary to learn it for
real, because you know the end result already, it is just figuring
out how it gets there.</li>
</ul>

<p>
I would like to believe that by doing so I am learning from my
mistakes that I made when trying to cram all the knowledge about one
field in my head (machine learning algorithms when doing the coursera
course. It would have been beneficial to know somy python so I could
graph the gradient descent and play with it, have some actual data to
work with and so on.. Instead of just staring at one algorithm).
</p>

<div id="outline-container-org5408180" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org5408180">To sum up</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org5408180">

<figure id="org74f058f">
<img src="./static/images/black-box2.png" alt="black-box2.png" width="1200px">

</figure>

<p>
Whether you choose to use it or not is up to you, but it can’t hurt,
for sure. It takes a really short time, like mere minutes for a single
topic. It involves information that you would eventually have to learn
anyway and it also gives you a brief but sufficient (sufficient for
using it) introduction to topics, allowing you to use them much
quicker than you would be able to if you decide to learn them all
fully in sequence.
</p>

<p>
p.s. damn it takes a lot of time to write this html document in a
proper way. I sometimes miss Word document, but sometimes I don't. Vim
has it's own advantages, but I am new with it so I am a little bit
slow. Learned how to yank, paste a word or a whole line today.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="taglist"><a href="https://arvydasg.github.io/tags.html">Tags</a>: <a href="https://arvydasg.github.io/tag-learning.html">learning</a> </div>]]></description>
  <category><![CDATA[learning]]></category>
  <link>https://arvydasg.github.io/2021-03-15-black-box-method.html</link>
  <guid>https://arvydasg.github.io/2021-03-15-black-box-method.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 16:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[Excel Stuff]]></title>
  <description><![CDATA[

<figure id="org919dd59">
<img src="./static/images/excel-fun.png" alt="excel-fun.png" width="1200px">

</figure>

<p>
I would really like to have some actual data to work with, but I can
not find any that I would 1-know how to read, 2-know how to work with,
3-would not get frustrated just by looking at csv file full of digits
and and commas.
</p>

<p>
Creating my own dataset just by typing words and numbers in a google
sheet is possible(and probably I will end up doing that and using what
I come up with for the next two weeks), but&#x2026; I forgot what I wanted
to say.
</p>

<p>
The thing is, according to my "plan" I am supposed to be learning
about excel and statistics right now, but for some reason as I watch a
tutorial or read a book (think stats) I come up to a road block which
tells me that to continue you need to know how to use python or how to
use excel. 1-I dont know how to use python and I am supposed to learn
in in 2 weeks(according to my plan :D) and 2-I dont have excel on my
computer (need to install in on linux through vine after finding a
free ISO&#x2026;) and google sheets lacks some functions that I see
tutorials about&#x2026;
</p>

<p>
Again, I don't feel that I am progressing anywhere, I am just looking
at various ways to get data, learning about various types of data and
basically finding out ways of how NOT to start learning DS :D But it's
alright, I'll get there.
</p>

<p>
Lets focus on excel for the rest of today. 16:20
</p>

<p>
Filters in excel a quite useful.
</p>

<p>
<b>Filters</b> in - <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wMlTDXPEjag&amp;t=21s">excel</a> are quite useful. Watching in 1.5x speed just to
get an idea of what is possible. Totals, nice. Transform your data
into a table to get an easy totals/averages and so on. You get not
only filering options but also your forumulas or charts referencing
the data - they both get updated. Kay, will keep in mind.
</p>

<p>
Formulas and Functions by the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Jl0Qk63z2ZY">guy</a> who works at Microsoft :D.
</p>

<p>
Been seeing median here and there, so here is a refresher:
</p>


<figure id="org7246a7a">
<img src="./static/images/median-math-is-fun.png" alt="median-math-is-fun.png" width="1200px">

</figure>

<p>
<b>Concatenate</b> - =CONCAT(x1,x2) takes value from one row, then from the
other one that you selec and separate with comman and puts them
together in one "langeli".
</p>

<p>
<b>If</b> - <code>IF(D13</code>"smile", "yay", "boo") good times Csongor, good times ;) IF
a field equals to a word "smile", the returned value will be "yay", if
the field equals to anything else than "smile", returns the value
"boo".
</p>

<p>
<b>Countif</b> - Selecting a range of values and asking the formula to
calculate how many instances that we have specied are in the given
range. For example. =COUNTIF(B1:G7, 1) formula presents me with a
number that tells me how many numbers "1" are in the field that I
asked to look in.
</p>

<p>
<b>Vlookup</b> - things are getting more interesting. So Vlookup looks at the
table, lest say the table has two values&#x2026; you know, let me just put
an image rly quick (more vim and html practice on top of that).
</p>


<figure id="org6aa29aa">
<img src="./static/images/vlookup.png" alt="vlookup.png" width="1200px">

</figure>

<p>
So the formula that found out the favorite color of ciongibongi is as
such - =VLOOKUP(D18,D15:E18,2,FALSE)
</p>

<p>
<b>Sumif</b> - is a nice function I guess but wont make an example, I am
aware of it alright.
</p>

<p>
p.s. damn it takes a lot of time to write this html document in a
proper way. I sometimes miss Word document, but sometimes I don't. Vim
has it's own advantages, but I am new with it so I am a little bit
slow. Learned how to yank, paste a word or a whole line today.
</p>
<div class="taglist"><a href="https://arvydasg.github.io/tags.html">Tags</a>: <a href="https://arvydasg.github.io/tag-learning.html">learning</a> </div>]]></description>
  <category><![CDATA[learning]]></category>
  <link>https://arvydasg.github.io/2021-03-15-excel-stuff.html</link>
  <guid>https://arvydasg.github.io/2021-03-15-excel-stuff.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 16:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[Thoughts on Achieving Goals]]></title>
  <description><![CDATA[
<p>
How good is it to work 24/7 on one particular thing?
</p>

<p>
Might Look like a great idea, you will get accoomplished a lot, right?
But only in one area. F.x. Programming. But what about your health,
the body that actually allows you to be learning this stuff. Who will
take care of it? Diet, exercise, mobility, simply movement. Who will
take care of all the other things in your life And all of this is
CRUCIAL for being productive, really. You can not have NO food and be
productive. You can not have breaks where you exercise because you
wont clear you head, find new ideas and at the same time train your
mind. You must do those. Damn balance is very very important. Have to
have everything in your life in order to be good at one particular
thing, no? But hm there are examples of people who are super super
good at one subject and suck at others. Like programmers f.x, they
dont rally care about their bodies right? But its probably the battle
you choose.. I personally think its important for me to take care of
my body first and ONLY and WHEN I do that I will be productive and
find time for other things. Just like at 12th grade, remember? You had
so many things on your to do list and managed to do all of them. The
more busy you are the more you can accomplish. Books, guitar,
exercise, cold showers, food, programming, shop, relatives, friends,
etc etc are all possible and should be tried to be managed. Like in
todays video - streching video Says the more you strech per day doesn't
increse the benefits, but that frequency of 6 days a week and 5
minutes total for that week is what's important. 6 days a week 5
minutes total = yield best streching results, more is simply not
necessary. This shocked me a little, simply because I agree on it and
I was acting completely different the entire last month. I would think
that I am working just because I am spending a lot of time on it, but
I was simply staying in place in terms of my progress.
</p>

<p>
Look at yourself now. Today, its 11am, you ate, you have already found
time to learn about calculus and feel good about the direction you are
going to. You did run for 10 or so mins, you did 4x10 squats with 10kg
on your back, you wanted to go to the shop but didnt take your mask
with you, you came back and took a cold shower, got into fresh clothes
and went back to study and now you are even doing stuff with your
website. All of this would not have been possible if I would have
stayed with the previous or Lex Fridman mindset to focus on one thing
only. Not Lex, its mostly mine, because I have been like this my whole
life. It is either ALL or NOTHING. But maybe the middle path is the
right choice, right, Candy?
</p>

<div id="outline-container-org9a26061" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org9a26061">Parkinson's Law</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org9a26061">
<p>
Parkinson's Law is the old adage that work expands to fill the time
allotted. Put simply, the amount of work required adjusts to the time
available for its completion.
</p>

<p>
It also illustrates very well what I was expriencing. The more time I
have, the more work will appear. But as we have seen from the
streching example - more work does not necessarily bring better
results.
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org6140664" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org6140664">But does it then mean</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org6140664">
<p>
That in order to have a productive DAY you also have to balance out
the work and relaxation? 50% 50%?;)
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="taglist"><a href="https://arvydasg.github.io/tags.html">Tags</a>: <a href="https://arvydasg.github.io/tag-personal.html">personal</a> </div>]]></description>
  <category><![CDATA[personal]]></category>
  <link>https://arvydasg.github.io/2021-03-15-thoughts-on-achieving-goals.html</link>
  <guid>https://arvydasg.github.io/2021-03-15-thoughts-on-achieving-goals.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 16:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[Addict]]></title>
  <description><![CDATA[
<p>
When I am learning without a plan or an idea of what I am doing, I get
in this mode of constant kind of anxiety, feeling that I can ONLY
spend my time of the things I am trying to learn, that god forbid I
will waste some time by washing clothes or getting a shave or
something - all that seems like a waste of time.
</p>

<p>
But now, since I am more relaxed, following the pomodoro technique,
ticking off things from my sunday to-do list, it is only 11:30 and I
have already done a lot of things that help to keep my days(life) in
balance. AND at the same time I still have loads of time to do HOURS
of learning. Productive time, with calm mind, because other things are
sorted and not at the back of my mind.
</p>

<p>
I used to be this person that gets into an "addiction" kind of mode
trying to complete and perfect a task (Revit in Denmark, Garden in
Nepal, linux and other things now). Nothing else is important, only me
and the task. I am forced to believe that this is a bad trait and I am
kind of relieved thinking about it as a bad trait, because I don't get
as much work done by taking care other things in my life, but what I
realized, that the “addiction” type of work mode didn't actually get
me a lot of work done. I was just staring at the material without
understanding what it was about. So most of my effort went into the
task and only small amount of it was actually productive.
</p>

<p>
Really, for the next 6 months I will be doing this passive learning.
Now it sounds good, I like it, I got structure, I have a path, I have
the reasons “why”, now all I have to do is follow that path. It's all
on me now.
</p>

<p>
5mins to write this and its so good. Just dumped it out.
</p>

<p>
p.s. Okay, I have re-read this after some hours and I see it doesn't
really make much sence if you are not ME. I think I won't always try
to make my "brain dump" material clearly understandable by others. For
now, all of this is purely for me. To practice working on a keyboard,
to practice using vim, to practice building website pages from time
to time. So yeah :)
</p>
<div class="taglist"><a href="https://arvydasg.github.io/tags.html">Tags</a>: <a href="https://arvydasg.github.io/tag-personal.html">personal</a> </div>]]></description>
  <category><![CDATA[personal]]></category>
  <link>https://arvydasg.github.io/2021-03-14-addict.html</link>
  <guid>https://arvydasg.github.io/2021-03-14-addict.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[Focused and Difused learning]]></title>
  <description><![CDATA[

<figure id="orgf539292">
<img src="./static/images/focused-diffuse.png" alt="focused-diffuse.png" width="1200px">

</figure>

<p>
The diffuse mode could be thought of as a flashlight set so that it
casts its light very broadly, but not very strongly in any one area.
(As opposed to the focused mode, which would have its light cast very
strongly in a single area, but very weakly everywhere else). Focused -
The type of thinking you need to do when you are trying to understand
something new.
</p>


<figure id="org97df70b">
<img src="./static/images/learning-flashlight.jpeg" alt="learning-flashlight.jpeg" width="1200px">

</figure>

<div id="outline-container-orga100cdf" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="orga100cdf">Focused mode</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orga100cdf">
<p>
<b>Focused mode</b> - like paintball. Think of something, the thought goes
from one neuron to the other. As it is bouncing on the bumpers, you
are able to solve a problem of something you are rather familiar with.
Thought moves smoothly along the already existing neural pathway -
moving on a familiar, nicely paved road.
</p>

<p>
Trying to do a multiplication problem or looking for a certain word in
your mind - probably stepping along the familiar pathways of the
focused mode.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org8f4b00a" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org8f4b00a">Diffuse mode</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org8f4b00a">
<p>
<b>Diffused thinking</b> - relaxed. You haven't thought before - you don't
know where the pattern\path is. All the other neurons are blocking the
patterns. New neural pathways have a way to appear, because you don't
bump into anything. (diffused mode).
</p>

<p>
If you are trying to solve a new problem it often cries out for the
more broad ranging perspectives of the diffuse mode.
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li><b>Dancing</b> in a relaxed and free form manner, without concentrating on anything</li>

<li>arouse the diffuse(rather than focused) mode.</li>

<li>Tag along in the passenger seaet of a car, looking absently out the window while someone else is driving.</li>

<li>Arouse the diffuse(rather than focused) mode.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org501ccd3" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org501ccd3">Can't have both</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org501ccd3">
<p>
When we find ourselves stuck on a problem, or even if we’re unsure of
a situation, the course of living our daily life. It's often a good
idea once you’ve focused directly on the situation to let things
settle back and take a bit more time. That way more neural processing
can take place, often below conscious awareness in the diffuse mode.
</p>

<p>
One mode limits the access to the other type of mode. Either one or
the other side of the coin, can not have both, same with thinking
modes. Either one or the other type of thinking.
</p>


<figure id="org515b29f">
<img src="./static/images/salvador-sleep.jpg" alt="salvador-sleep.jpg" width="1200px">

</figure>

<p>
<b>Salvador Dali</b> - Relaxing in the chair, vaguely thinking what he was
previously focusing on, holding keys, falling asleep, then when the
keys fall down, he wakes up and then goes to paint with the new
connections that he has just made while in the diffuse mode.
</p>

<p>
He suggests that the elements of creativity process are Preparation–
know your domain, Concentration– intense focus, Incubation– relax and
do something the polar opposite, Illumination– breakthrough on the
ideas and Verification– test the idea.
</p>

<p>
Salvador Dali also wrote a book called the ‘Fifty secrets of Magic
Craftsmanship'(1948)
</p>


<figure id="orge1d3ab9">
<img src="./static/images/thomas-edison.png" alt="thomas-edison.png" width="1200px">

</figure>

<p>
<b>Thomas Edison</b> did something similar.
</p>

<p>
During his day, Edison would take time out by himself and relax in a
chair or on a sofa. Invariably he would be working on a new invention
and seeking creative solutions to the problem he was dealing with. He
knew that if her could get into that "twilight state" between being
awake and being asleep, he could access the pure creative genius of
his subconscious mind.
</p>

<p>
To prevent himself from crossing all the way over the "genius gap"
into deep sleep, he would nap with his hand propped up on his elbow
while he clutched a handful of ball-bearings. Then he would just drift
off to sleep, knowing that his subconscious mind would take up the
challenge of his problem and provide a solution. As soon as he went
into too deep a sleep, his hand would drop and the ball-bearings would
spill noisily on the floor, waking him up again. He'd then write down
whatever was in his mind.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org60e2c77" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org60e2c77">Sum up</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org60e2c77">
<p>
Mind needs to go from one to the other mode to learn effectively.
</p>

<p>
Learning something difficult takes time. Brain needs to alternate its
ways of learning as it grapples with and assimilates the new material.
</p>

<p>
To gain muscles you need to work everyday. Little work everyday,
gradually allow yourself to grow. A LITTLE BIT EVERYDAY!!! Thank you
lady for making me change my mind about learning and being productive.
</p>


<figure id="orgaa30e8c">
<img src="./static/images/focused-diffuse1.png" alt="focused-diffuse1.png" width="1200px">

</figure>


<figure id="orgd6f4f42">
<img src="./static/images/learn-quiz.png" alt="learn-quiz.png" width="1200px">

</figure>

<p>
What a brilliant quiz.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="taglist"><a href="https://arvydasg.github.io/tags.html">Tags</a>: <a href="https://arvydasg.github.io/tag-learning.html">learning</a> </div>]]></description>
  <category><![CDATA[learning]]></category>
  <link>https://arvydasg.github.io/2021-03-13-focused-and-difused-learning.html</link>
  <guid>https://arvydasg.github.io/2021-03-13-focused-and-difused-learning.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 13 Mar 2021 17:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
